<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves lately come on the last day of Februarie 1591. from diuers partes of France, Sauoy, and Tripoli in Soria. Truely translated out of the French and Italian copies, as they were sent to right honourable persons</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112657</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847903</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847903</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12967</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01169)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12967)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 241:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves lately come on the last day of Februarie 1591. from diuers partes of France, Sauoy, and Tripoli in Soria. Truely translated out of the French and Italian copies, as they were sent to right honourable persons</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be sold at his shop, ouer against the great South doore of S. Paule,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Newes out of France.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Italy --  History --  1559-1789 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12967:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12967:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEWES Lately come on the laſt <hi>day of Februarie</hi> 1591. <hi>from diuers</hi> partes of France, Sauoy, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poli in Soria.</p>
            <p>Truely tranſlated out of the French and Italian Copies, as they were ſent to right Honourable perſons.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John Wolfe (</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be ſold at his ſhop, ouer againſt the great South doore of S. Paule. 1591.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:12967:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of St. George slaying the dragon</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="newsbook">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12967:2"/>
            <head>Newes latelie come on the laſt day of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary 1591. From diuers parts of France, Sauoy, and Tripoly in Soria. Truelie tranſlated out of the French and Italian coppies, as they were ſent to right Honorable perſons.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE King accompanied with his own forces, and the Marſhall Birons ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a long time laine about Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, hoping in the end to reduce the Citty to his deuotion, and perceiuing it a very harde thing to obtaine the ſame by main force, vnles it were by ſurpriſe, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſtrength of the ſame both by Art and nature, though there were very fewe Souldiers or none in it, except the Cittizens and Townes-men thereof:</p>
            <p>About the fouretéenth of February laſt, hee diuided himſelfe from the Marſhall Biron, and faigned to giue ouer the ſiedge, and to goe towards Dreur, hauing firſt giuen out that hee would goe to beſiege that towne, and went but two or thrée miles from Chartres. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall Biron, ſéeming the next day to leaue the ſiege, and to followe the King, as if he diſpaired to doe any good there, which thoſe of Chartres perceiuing, they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with ſuch Souldiers as they had, reſolued themſelues to make a ſaly, and to ſette vppon the reareward of the Marſhall as hee was marching towards Dreur, which accordingly they did, and iſſuing out of the Town moſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12967:3"/>brauely charged the Marſhalls hinder troupes, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall at firſt ſéemed to make hed againſt them, but ſoone after began to retire himſelfe, and to giue his ennemies place, and they nothing miſdoubting of any ſuch Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem, followed him amaine, continually ſkirmiſhing vntill they came about two miles from the Towne. In the meane time, the King lying there abouts in ambuſh, when hee ſawe his time, entred betweene the Towne and the men thereof that followed the Marſhall, and ſo couragiouſly charged them behinde, and the Marſhall then turning face towards them againe, that in leſſe then an houre that they fought, they ſlue them all, except thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Cuiraſſes which very hardly eſcaped.</p>
            <p>The King following the victory, entred preſently one of the Subburbes of Chartres, the Townes men ſeeing this, beganne to make a motion of peace with him, and offered to deliuer him the town &amp; fifty thouſand crowns, vppon condition, that he would remoue his forces, and place no Garriſon therein, which the King refuſed to do, and thereupon prepared to batter the Towne in two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, hauing reſolued not to leaue it vntill he haue gotten it. And it is verily belieued that he is in it already, which if he be, we are greatly bound to giue God thanks for it, for as much as thoſe of Paris will greatly be hindred by the ſame, for that they had moſt of their victuals from thoſe quarters thereabouts.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Deguidieres</hi> deputie Lieutenant for the king in the prouince of <hi>Dalphinate</hi> hath of late ſo hotely purſued the Dukes of <hi>Sauoyes</hi> forces that he entred his cittie of <hi>Ciamberie</hi> (chiefe parlament towne of <hi>Sauoy</hi>) and ſacked and ſpoiled the ſame, and then loden with the rich praye thereof, left it, foraſmuch as he had not forces ſufficient with him to keepe and munite the ſame, and ſo withdrew him ſelfe home againe without any loſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſaide Lorde <hi>Deguidieres</hi> returning home
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12967:3"/>from <hi>Ciamberie</hi> into <hi>Dalphinate</hi> met with the Duke of <hi>Nemours</hi> and his forces (who knowing the abſence of the gouernour thought to haue ſurpriſed ſome townes) and ſo charged him that he ſlue moſt of his Cauallarie and made him retire toward <hi>Lions,</hi> (whereof the Duke is gouernour) whither the Lorde <hi>Deguidieres</hi> did ſo ſtoutly follow him, that thoſe of <hi>Lions</hi> fearing leaſt hee would entrench him ſelfe in their Suburbe called <hi>Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lottiere,</hi> adioyning to the gate of Rodan, and is a verie faire, long, and rich Suburbe, ſet fire to the ſame, and haue cleane burnt it vp: but he withdrew him ſelfe into his owne gouernment, where he hath ſo honourably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued himſelfe, that hee hath in a maner reduced the whole Prouince to the obedience and deuotion of the King, and is ſuch a terror to his enimies, that none dare ſtirre.</p>
            <p>The King of Spaine had commaunded certaine Cornets of horſemen of Naples, to come downe from thence to the Duke of Sauoy, that with them he might infeſt and trouble thoſe of Dalphinate, in as much as they were horſes of more ſwiftneſſe and ſpeede then hee hath any, but the Lord <hi>Deguidieres</hi> hauing met with them, hath altogether defeated them, that verie few or none hath eſcaped him.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of Geneua haue lately taken a forte called the forte of Saint <hi>Catherin,</hi> not verie farre from Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua, which the Duke hath not long ſince cauſed to bee built onely to vere them, and they haue razed the ſame, and haue gone ſpoiling, waſting and burning ſo farre as Nantua, which is two dayes iourney from Geneua.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of Air in Prouence, with all the countrie there aboutes are in a mutinie and tumult againſt the Duke of Sauoy (to whom they had voluntarily giuen them ſelues) foraſmuch as he went about to build a Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadel in Air, which they by no meanes will ſuffer.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:12967:4"/>
            <p> The cittie of Marſeille which with the greater part of the countrie of Prouence (through the faire promiſes and inſtigations of the King of Spaine) had accepted the Duke of Sauoy to be their Protector, and in ſigne of that, aduanced the ſtandard of the holy League (which is a crucifixe) hath of late vpon the tumult of Air reuolted from him, and erected the Armes of Fraunce, and doth publiſh that it holdeth and will holde for the king of France.</p>
            <p>Certaine Iacopin Friers of the cittie of Terracon, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate vpon the riuer of Rodanum, together with ſome euil minded Citizens therof, had practiſed to giue the citty to the Duke of Sauoy, of whom they had receiued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faire and large promiſes: and hauing agreed both of the meanes and time, the gouernour of the cittie hauing had ſome inteligence thereof, and diſcouered their whole platforme, one night before their treaſon ſhoulde haue beene effected, cauſed the Iacopins and all their complices to be taken and laide in ſundrie priſons, and that verie night ſent certaine of his companies out of the towne there to lye in an ambuſh, vntil ſuch time as they ſhould heare thrée ſtrokes of a Bel, which was the watch-word betwéen the Iacopins and the Duke of Sauoys Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. All this being thus appointed, the Dukes forces came to the cittie, who ſo ſoone as they were neare the gate, at which they ſhoulde haue beene let in: the Bell was ſtriken thrée times, where preſently the Ambuſh that was laide without the towne aſſaulted them, and thoſe of the cittie which ſtood prepared to receiue them, opened the gates and ſailied out vpon them, where in leſſe then halfe an houre the Dukes men being ſo ſurpriſed in the middeſt were euery man ſlaine, and their Captaine ſo ſore hurt, that he dyed two dayes after, ſo was the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie reſerued for the King, for whom it holdeth ſtil.</p>
            <p>The Duke of Sauoye is of late fallen into a conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12967:4"/>and lieth very ſicke at Nizza, ſo that his Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe deſpaire of his recouery.</p>
            <p>The Lord Chatillion hath of late had the Lord <hi>de la Chaſtres</hi> in chaſe, and hath ſo nearely purſued him that hee hath driuen him to Chaſteauneuf, where hee doth ſtraightly beſiege him, and is in hope to haue him, if hee may haue ordinance to batter the Towne.</p>
            <p>By letters from Aleppo, and Tripoly in Soria the twenty ninth of December, and the ſecond of Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary laſt, it is written to diuers of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice, that in the confines of Paleſtina were newly ſtart vp two religious men, who vnder colour of a reformation in religion, and certaine plauſible orders which they would haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, name them ſelues Prophes ſent by God to illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the Maumetiſts, and to bring them out of darknes to eternall light, who had ſo many followers that it was wondrous to tell, and that one of them was gone with ten thouſand men to helpe the Perſians in his warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the great Turke, and the other kept ſtill about Paleſtina, and daily conquered great countries, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in forces and number of men, to the great terror of the Turkes.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
